Guide to the Association of Pacific Coast Geographers records 1935-2010
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Association of Pacific Coast Geographers records
1935-2010
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0082apcg
Association of Pacific Coast Geographers
5 linear feet
The Association of Pacific Coast Geographers was founded in 1935 to promote geographical education, research, and knowledge. The collection documents the Association's activities.
Founded in 1935 by a gathering of geographers including graduate students and faculty from universities, normal schools, and junior colleges, the Association of Pacific Coast Geographers has a long and rich history promoting geographical education, research, and knowledge. Since 1952 it has also been the Pacific Coast Regional Division of the Association of American Geographers, serving AK, AZ, CA, HI, ID, NV, OR, WA, BC, and YT.
The Association of Pacific Coast Geographers records consist of a large selection of administrative files including committee and officers' files, correspondence, financial records, membership lists, and directories. There are also records from the association's annual meetings, arranged according to location, including photographs depicting various association officers and activities, as well as publications and communications including newsletters, yearbooks, and compilations of essays.
The Association of Pacific Coast Geographers records are organized according to the following series arrangement:
Series I. Administrative Files 1935-2003
Series II. Annual Meetings 1938-2008
Series III. Photographs 1992-2003
Series IV. Publications / Communications 1935-2010
The collection is open to the public.
Donated by the Association of Pacific Coast Geographers, date unknown.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Association of Pacific Coast Geographers--Archives
Bellingham (Wash.)--History--Sources; Northwest Coast of North America--History--Sources
Geography--Pacific States--History--Sources
Science; Bellingham
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Administrative Files, 1935-2003; Series I
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 1962 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1936-1998 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Committee Files
    - Executive Committee, 1986-2003 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Nominating Committee, 1959-1985 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Annual Chair Committee Meeting Items, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Awards Committee
      - Committee Items and Correspondence, 1968-1997 (Box-folder 1/6)
      - Geopub Awards, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Stella Louie Award, 1976-1984 (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Distinguished Service Awards, 1984-1992 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Membership Committee
      - Committee Items and Correspondence, 1971-1996 (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Membership Lists and Correspondence, 1972-1978 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Yearbook Committee
      - Ad hoc Yearbook Committee, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 1/12)
      - Committee Items and Correspondence, 1977-1996 (Box-folder 1/13)
      - Correspondence re: yearbook articles for reprinting, 1971-1990 (Box-folder 1/14)
      - Correspondence with O.S.U. Press, 1964-1988 (Box-folder 1/15)
      - Materials on History of Geography Department, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Officer's Files
    - List of Officers, Meeting Places, 1935-1999 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - President's Files
      - Notes for Incoming Presidents, 1958-1991 (Box-folder 1/18)
      - Daniel Arreola, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 1/19)
      - Joan Clemens, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 1/20)
      - Court, Arnold, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 1/21)
      - William Crowley, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 1/22)
      - Robert Durrenberger, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 1/23)
      - Larry Ford, 1983 (Box-folder 1/24)
      - Chris Field, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1/25)
      - Lay T. Gibson, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 1/26)
      - Richard M. Highsmith Jr., 1965 (Box-folder 1/27)
      - Martin Kaatz, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1/28)
      - Earl W. Kersten, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 1/29)
      - Terrill J. Kramer, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 1/30)
      - David W. Lambis, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1/31)
      - Bill Loy, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 1/32)
      - Dan Luten, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1/33)
      - Elliot McIntire, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 1/34)
      - Tom McKnight, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1/35)
      - Howard Nelson, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1/36)
      - Clyde Patton, 1967 (Box-folder 1/37)
      - Edward Price, 1968 (Box-folder 1/38)
      - Larry Price, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 1/39)
      - Phil Pryde, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 1/40)
      - Lester B. Rowntree, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1/41)
      - Jim Scott, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1/42)
      - Dan Stanislawski, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1/43)
      - Rod Steineri, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2/1)
      - William Thomas, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2/2)
      - Margaret Trussell, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Alvin Urquhart, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Phil Wagner, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Secretary/Treasurer's Files
      - James Ashbaugh, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 2/6)
      - Dale Courtney, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Howard J. Critchfield, 1955 (Box-folder 2/8)
      - Art Earick, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 2/9)
      - John F. Gaines, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 2/10)
      - Paul F. Griffin, 1960 (Box-folder 2/11)
      - Gary Klee, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 2/12)
      - Fritz Kramer, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 2/13)
      - Terrill Kramer, 1981-1986 (Box-folder 2/14)
      - Robert L. Monahan, 1964-1967 (Box-folder 2/15)
      - Margaret Trussell, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2/16)
      - Nancy Williamson, 1989 (Box-folder 2/17)
    - Editor's Files
      - John Gaines, 1967-1973 (Box-folder 2/18)
      - Robert L. Monahan, 1977 (Box-folder 2/19)
      - James W. Scott, 1979-1987 (Box-folder 2/20)
      - Rod Steiner, 1975 (Box-folder 2/21)
    - General Officer's Files
      - Newsletter Editor
        - Items re: Appointment of Yearbook Editor, 1987 (Box-folder 2/22)
        - Newsletter Editor Correspondence, 1968-1977 (Box-folder 2/23)
        - Newsletters and Pacifica Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 2/24)
        - Treasurer's Reports, 1951-1998 (Box-folder 2/25)
        - Regional Councilor Materials, 1970-1992 (Box-folder 2/26)
        - Archivist's Materials, 1968-1998 (Box-folder 2/27)
  - Women Geographers
    - Women Geographer's Group, 1986-1995 (Box-folder 2/28)
  - Correspondence
    - Regular Correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 2/29)
    - Fiscal Year, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2/30)
    - Fiscal Year, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 2/31)
    - Fiscal Year, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2/32)
    - Email Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 2/33)
    - IGC Washington, 1992 (Box-folder 2/34)
    - AAG, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 2/35)
  - Financial Materials
    - Account Book, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 2/36)
    - Account Book, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 2/37)
    - Account Book, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2/38)
    - Account Book, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 2/39)
    - IRS Materials, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 2/40)
    - Tax Exemption Application, 1970 (Box-folder 2/41)
  - Membership Lists and Directories
    - Membership Lists, 1951-1952; 1954; 1956-1957; 1959 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Membership Lists, 1963; 1965; 1968-1970; 1972; 1975-1976 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Membership Lists, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Membership Lists, 1980-1981; 1986; 1988; 1991; 1996; 1999 (Box-folder 3/4)
- Annual Meetings, 1938-2008; Series II
  - San Diego, 1938 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - UBC Vancouver, 1949 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Salt Lake City, 1950 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - USC, 1951 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Cheney, 1951 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Corvallis, 1952 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Santa Barbara, 1953 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - WSU Pullman, 1954 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - UW Seattle, 1956 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Stanford, 1957 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Eugene, 1960 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - San Francisco, 1961 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - UW Seattle, 1962 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Los Angeles City College, 1963 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Berkeley, 1964 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Portland, 1965 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Riverside, CA, 1966 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Chico, CA, 1967 (Box-folder 3/22)
  - Bellingham, 1968 (Box-folder 3/23)
  - San Fernando State College, 1969 (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Santa Cruz, 1970 (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Victoria B.C., 1971 (Box-folder 3/26)
  - Hayward, 1972 (Box-folder 3/27)
  - San Diego, 1973 (Box-folder 3/28)
  - Corvallis, 1974 (Box-folder 3/29)
  - Fresno, 1975 (Box-folder 3/30)
  - Tucson, 1976 (Box-folder 3/31)
  - Hilo, Hawaii, 1977 (Box-folder 3/32)
  - Portland, 1978 (Box-folder 3/33)
  - Santa Barbara, 1979 (Box-folder 3/34)
  - Reno, 1980 (Box-folder 3/35)
  - Moscow, ID, 1981 (Box-folder 3/36)
  - Long Beach, 1982 (Box-folder 3/37)
  - Eureka, CA, 1983 (Box-folder 3/38)
  - Cheney, 1984 (Box-folder 3/39)
  - UCLA, 1985 (Box-folder 3/40)
  - Eugene, 1986 (Box-folder 3/41)
  - Davis, 1987 (Box-folder 3/42)
  - San Diego, 1988 (Box-folder 3/43)
  - Fairbanks, AK, 1989 (Box-folder 3/44)
  - Chico, CA, 1990 (Box-folder 3/45)
  - Tucson, 1991 (Box-folder 3/46)
  - Bellingham, 1992 (Box-folder 3/47)
  - Berkeley, 1993 (Box-folder 3/48)
  - Northridge, 1994 (Box-folder 3/49)
  - Sonoma State University, 1995 (Box-folder 3/50)
  - Sacramento, 1996 (Box-folder 3/51)
  - Spokane, 1997 (Box-folder 3/52)
  - Flagstaff, AZ, 1998 (Box-folder 3/53)
  - Reno, 1999 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Arcata, CA, 2000 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Santa Barbara, CA, 2001 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - San Bernardino, CA, 2002 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Portland, 2003 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - San Luis Obispo, CA, 2004 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Phoenix, 2005 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Eugene, OR, 2006 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Long Beach, 2007 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Fairbanks, AK, 2008 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Business Meeting Minutes, 1954-1967 (Box-folder 4/11)
- Photographs, 1992-2003; Series III
  - Annual Meeting Photographs
    - Photographs from Helen Proctor, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 4/12)
    - Annual Meeting, 1995 (Box-folder 4/13)
    - Spokane, Bill Loy, 1997 (Box-folder 4/14)
    - Annual Meeting, Joan Clement, 1997 (Box-folder 4/15)
    - Annual Meeting, Bill Loy, 1998 (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Annual Meeting, Bill Loy, 1999 (Box-folder 4/17)
    - Annual Meeting, Bill Loy, 2003 (Box-folder 4/18)
  - Officer's Photographs
    - President and other officer's photographs, 1992 (Box-folder 4/19)
- Publications / Communications, 1935-2010; Series IV
  - Applied Geographers preliminary issues, 1978-2009 (Box-folder 4/20)
  - Blumenstock Memorial Volume materials, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 4/21)
  - Materials regarding the Death of Jeremy Anderson, 1987 (Box-folder 4/22)
  - Newsletters
    - Newsletters, 1940s (Box-folder 4/23)
    - Newsletters, 1950s (Box-folder 4/24)
    - Newsletters, 1960s (Box-folder 4/25)
    - Newsletters, 1970s (Box-folder 4/26)
    - Newsletters, 1980s (Box-folder 4/27)
    - Newsletters, 1990s (Box-folder 4/28)
    - Newsletters, 2000-2010 (Box-folder 4/29)
  - Yearbooks
    - Index, 1941-1949 (Box 5)
    - An Author Index of Articles and Abstracts in the Yearbooks of the APCG vols. 1-10, 1935-1948 (Box 5)
    - Yearbooks, 1935-1942; 1947-1967; 1969-1990; 1994-1996; 2007-2008; 2010 (Box 5)
  - Sauer Volume
    - Sauer and Geographic Influences correspondence, 1977-1981 (Box 5)
    - Special Sauer Volume Materials, 1984-1986 (Box 5)
    - Kenzer, Martin S., ed. Carl O. Sauer: A Tribute. Corvallis, OR: Oregon State University Press for the Association of Pacific Coast Geographers (includes negatives), 1987 (Box 5)
  - Court, Arnold, ed. Eclectic Climatology: Selected Essays Written in Memory of David I. Blumenstock, 1913-1963. Corvallis, OR: Oregon State University Press, 1968 (Box 5)